Guide to the Isaac James Quillen Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Isaac James Quillen papers
1931-1967
SC0488
Quillen, Isaac James, 1909-
25.5 Linear feet
The papers document Quillen's graduate work at Yale, his teaching career at Stanford University, his writings and publications, and his research interests. Included are his papers while at Yale; syllabi, exams, and other course materials; drafts of his books; correspondence files with his publisher Scott, Foresman; files from his work with UNESCO; speeches, lectures, and articles; and research and lecture notecards. The papers also contain personal correspondence, including some of his wife Viola Quillen; financial records, including some for the Gazos Creek Tree Farm, a joint project with Prof. Paul Hanna; and photographs, including several of the Quillens' home designed by Ernest Born.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of the estate of Mrs. I. James Quillen, 1995.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
I. James Quillen joined the Stanford faculty of the School of Education in 1936. He was appointed full professor of education in 1946 and served as Dean of the School of Education from 1953 to 1966, when he was appointed Professor Emeritus. Before joining the Stanford faculty, he taught in the public schools of Delaware and at Colorado State College of Education. In 1944, he was president of the National Council for the Social Studies. He was an official of the UNESCO secretariat in Paris in 1948-49, serving as acting head of the UNESCO Department of Education during part of that time. He died in 1967.
Description of the Collection
The papers document Quillen's graduate work at Yale, his teaching career at Stanford University, his writings and publications, and his research interests. Included are his papers while at Yale; syllabi, exams, and other course materials; drafts of his books; correspondence files with his publisher Scott, Foresman; files from his work with UNESCO; speeches, lectures, and articles; and research and lecture notecards. The papers also contain personal correspondence, including some of his wife Viola Quillen; financial records, including some for the Gazos Creek Tree Farm, a joint project with Prof. Paul Hanna; and photographs, including several of the Quillens' home designed by Ernest Born.
Access Terms
Born, Ernest.; Gazos Creek Tree Farm.; Hanna, Paul Robert, 1902-1988.; Quillen, Isaac James, 1909-; Quillen, Viola.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education. Faculty.; United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.; Yale University --Students.; Education, Secondary--Curricula.; Education, Secondary--Study and teaching.; Examinations.; Photoprints.; Social sciences--Study and teaching (Secondary).; Syllabi.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Stanford Class 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Menlo Junior College 1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Yale University re degree 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Yale University re: Degree conferral 1931, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Yale Degree Conferral 1942-43 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - U of Chigago: Re Employment Offer 1945-46 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Stanford School of Education 1949-54 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - University of Delaware re: Commencement 1957-58 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Harvard School of Ed + Georgetown 1962-64 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Stanford U, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Publication of Contemporary Problems 1952-55 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Publication of Contemporary Problems ( cont.) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Publication of Education for Social Competence 1951, 1957, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Education for Social Competence Chapters 1-5 (revised) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Encyclopedia Britanica Junior (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Govt. Book 1951 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Govt. Book (cont) 1952-53 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Textbook Improvement and Intl. Understanding (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Proposed Text on Educational Sociology 1941 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Article for Journal of Childhood Education 1947 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Workbook for living in our America(40A) 1950-60 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Living in Our Communities (40c) 1958-62 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Living World History 1955-62 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Scott Fonsman (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Making the Goods We Need (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Geography + History Text (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Textbook Revisions (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Further Revisions 1945-60 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Further Revisions Cont. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Revision of Textbooks (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Publishing 1950-62 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Publishing 1951-53 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Revisions and Publishing 1958-62 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Selbyville History (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - McGraw Hill Co. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Coronet Instructional Films 1950-57 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Letter & Paper from Keppel (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - A.J Nystriom & Co. 1957-62 ( folder 1) (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - A.J Nystriom & Co. 1957-62 ( folder 2) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Corishel Instructional Films 1958-60 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Record 1959 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Project on the Instructional Program (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Equational Newsletters, Papers (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Study in Gary (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - National Journal for the Social Studies (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Liason Committee for Intontl Ed. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Intercultural Ed. Workshop (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - UNESCO 1947 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - UNESCO Nov, 1947 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - UNESCO 1948-49 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newsletters/ Papers Syllabi (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Newsletters/ Reports/ Speeches (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Conferences, Trips (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Activities 1948-51 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Activities 1949-50 ( Folder 1) (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Activities 1949-50 ( Folder 2) (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Activities 1949-51 ( Folder 1 of 4) (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Activities 1949-51 ( Folder 2 of 4) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Activities 1949-51 ( Folder 3 of 4) (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Activities 1949-51 ( Folder 4 of 4) (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - G.N Kefawor (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Sabbatical Trips (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Cowley to Quillen 1/4/54 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - John Saunders (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - General correspondence 1937-1974, notecards (Box 9)
  - Class syllabi, exams, notecards, and other course materials, arranged chronologically (Box 10)
  - Class syllabi, exams, notecards, and other course materials, arranged chronologically, continued (Box 11)
  - Personal Papers, Letters to Mrs. I. J. Quillen, Family Photographs, Investment Information, Legal Documents Insurance, Death Certificate, etc. (Box 12)
  - Slides, mostly from travels (Box 13)
  - Certificates and photographs (Box 14 os)
  - Class notes from Yale (Box 15)
  - Educational conferences (Box 16)
  - Educational conferences, continued (Box 17)
  - Quillen's projects away from Stanford (Box 18)
  - Newsletters of educational organizations (Box 19)
  - Papers on curriculum and education issues (Box 20)
  - Newspaper clippings collected by Quillen, 1957-66 (Box 21)
  - Papers by colleagues not at Stanford (Box 22)
  - Papers and speeches by Stanford colleagues (Box 23)
  - Various materials specific to Stanford (Box 24)
  - Various materials specific to Stanford, continued (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous professional papers and drafts of two books (Box 26-29)
  - Calendars, publications, photographs, and personal papers (Box 30-35)
  - Correspondence and notebooks of Viola Quillen (Box 36)
  - Quillen's notecards (Box 37-44)
  - Oversize memorabilia (Box 45)